Guide to the Dorothy Frooks Papers 1897-1984 MS 3116
New-York Historical Society
Dorothy Frooks papers
1897-1984
New-York Historical Society
Frooks, Dorothy, 1899-1997
MS 3116
9.25 Linear feet in 4 flat boxes and 2 record cartons
The Dorothy Frooks papers include newspaper clippings, event programs, correspondence, photographs, and other material that document the range of her life interests in veterans affairs, legal advocacy, politics, suffrage, Americanism, the legal and social relationship of men and women, and other matters. Much of this collection takes the form of scrapbooks compiled by Frooks.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
The collection is organized roughly in relation to the degree to which the documents were organized in the original collection as found when processed in 2019. Accordingly the most organized documents, Frooks's scrapbooks, are presented first. These are followed by a few files of thematic content found in the collection. The collection closes with folders of "various documents" that were pulled together by the processing archivist; those were arranged generally in chronological order.
Biographical / Historical
Dorothy Frooks (1899?-1997) was born in Saugerties, New York, the daughter of Reginald and Rosita (Siberez) Frooks. As a high school student in Bayonne, New Jersey, around 1911, Frooks gained renown for her public appearances in support of suffrage for women, earning the sobriquet the "Young Suffragette." With the advent of World War I, Frooks joined the Naval Reserve, employing her public speaking skills in the service of Liberty Loan campaigns and recruitment of servicemen. She was intensely patriotic and a believer in Americanism, and held that outlook through her long life.
Frooks earned a law degree from Hamilton Law School in Chicago and was admitted to the New York bar in 1920, becoming an attorney for a short time with the Salvation Army. Among the cases she handled as defense attorney in private practice in the late 1920s were two that received some national attention: the case of teenager Catherine Deninno, who was accused of killing the man who had impregnated her at age 12 and later attempted to blackmail her, and the case of Gloria Rouzer, a "society girl" held as a material witness in a Louisiana death.
Frooks was also an author, beginning in 1919 with her novel "The American Heart." She wrote both fiction and non-fiction through the 1940s, culminating with her autobiography "Lady Lawyer" in the 1970s. She edited the Oyster Bay News in the 1920s and later the Murray Hill News in the 1950s and 1960s. By the 1930s Frooks was deeply engaged with advocating for women veterans of WWI, and became national commander of Women World War Veterans Inc. Among the group's initiatives was founding a convalescent home for the aging veterans in the area of her birthplace, Saugerties. In the 1920s and 1930s, Frooks also tried her hand at politics, entering various primary elections, but losing them. As World War II approached, she advocated for peace, but when war was declared she was in full support of the United States as she had been during WWI. She joined the Women Army Corps and served with the Red Cross in various hospitals in the southern United States. She remained active in veterans' organizations into her late life.
A theme that emerges in much of Frooks's writing and her legal career was the relationship, especially legal, between men and women. Throughout her life Frooks moved in political, legal and military veteran circles commonly associated with men, though she also observed differences as expressed in the 1970s in her opposition to the proposed Equal Rights Amendment (ERA). Frooks, a founder as a young woman of a Bachelor's Girls Club, remained unmarried until late in life, in 1986 when she married Jay Philippe Vanderbilt.
(The above note was based on Frooks's obituary in the New York Times, Wikipedia entry, and documents in the collection.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dorothy Frooks, 1985.
Scope and Contents
The Dorothy Frooks papers include newspaper clippings, event programs, correspondence, photographs, and other material that document the range of her life interests in veterans affairs, legal advocacy, politics, suffrage, Americanism, the legal and social relationship of men and women, and other matters. Much of this collection takes the form of scrapbooks compiled by Frooks.
Related Materials
New York Public Library's Archives and Manuscripts Division holds additional Dorothy Frooks papers (MssCol 1091).
Clippings (information artifacts).; Photographs.; Printed ephemera.; Programs (documents).; Scrapbooks.; Liberty bonds; Man-woman relationships.; Political campaigns -- New York (State) -- New York; Suffragists -- United States.; Women authors; Women lawyers.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Veterans.; United States. Navy -- Recruiting, enlistment, etc. -- World War, 1914-1918.; Women World War Veterans, Inc.
- Scrapbook [#1], 1911-1912 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Clippings concerning Frooks, still a 16 year old high school student in Bayonne, NJ, and her involvement in the woman's suffrage movement.
- Scrapbook [#2], 1911-1918 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Clippings concerning Frooks's involvement with suffrage, social problems, flying an airplane, efforts at having men marry before going to fight in World War I, support for Liberty Bonds, founding the Bachelor Girls' Club. Includes an article by Frooks, identified as president of the Equal Justice League, from the New York City World (January 26, 1913). In addition to clippings has a copy of The Hudson Magazine (March 1911) with an article about Frooks and suffrage, four issues of Public Service Magazine edited by Frooks, and Vol 1/No. 1 of "American Patriot" magazine.
- Scrapbook [#3], 1922-1926 (Box 2)
  Clippings concerning Frook's legal career, including being admitted to the bar of the U.S. Supreme Court (1922), counsel for Salvation Army, and her defense of Catherine Denino, age 16, who killed the man who impregnated her at age 12 and later attempted to blackmail her; and clippings concerning her political career as candidate in the Republican congressional primaries from New York's 27th district (1920, 1922).
- Scrapbook [#4], 1917-1933 (Box 3)
  Clippings concerning Liberty Loan campaigning, ads for her book "The American Heart," becoming Salvation Army lawyer, Frook's 1922 congressional primary campaign, commentary columns by Frooks on legal issues between women and men, and other matters.
- Scrapbook [#5], 1917-1932 (Box 1)
  Clippings about Liberty Loan campaign and recruitment for soldiers during World War I; Catherine Denino and Gloria Rouzer/Ione Orde murder cases, and other of Frook's cases; membership in the Bachelor Girls' Club and, apparently false, reports of her engagement to Schuyler Vanderbilt; Frooks's negative view of men in relation to women; allegations by Frooks and others that the attendees of an American Legion convention in Paris were financially exploited (1927); lists of radio programs, including those with Frooks speaking on topic "Law for the Layman"; and some politics. Holds a few items of ephemera, including posters from Liberty Loan appearances in Kansas and admission tickets to the 1924 Democratic National Convention.
- Scrapbook [#6], 1926-1929, 1934-1935 (Box 3)
  Clippings on the Catherine Denino murder case (1926-27); Gloria Rouzer (a/k/a Ione Orde) murder case in Louisiana (1929); Frook's candidacy for Congress on the Law Preservation Party ticket, her related disagreements with Franklin D. and Eleanor Roosevelt, speculation on her running for U.S. President, and other political matters (1934-35); Frook's advocacy for a "bonus bill" for women veterans of World War I; her travels to Alaska; and her activities as commander/president of the Women World War Veterans.
- Scrapbook [#7], 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  A relatively small scrapbook with clippings, tearsheets and other documents. Includes original letter naming Frooks to the Committee of Reception for Amelia Earhart Putnam in New York (June 1932); letter from the Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences acknowledging Frooks will speak there on the legal topic of "Estates" (1932); articles by Frooks "The Objective of Women Widely Spread" (1924) and "Uncle Sam's Garden Island [Puerto Rico]" (December 1923); a political cartoon featuring Frooks sweeping out political corruption; and a publicity flyer for Frooks's book "Love's Law."
- Scrapbook [#8], 1933 October-1934 October (Box 3)
  Clippings on politics (including Frook's bid to be the Democratic congressional candidate from NY's 25th district), speaking engagements, legal matters.
- Scrapbook [#9], 1934 August-September (Box 1)
  Clippings on politics (including Frook's bid to be the Democratic congressional candidate from NY's 25th district), speaking engagements, legal matters, and her proposal to exempt property from taxes after 25 years.
- Scrapbook [#10], 1934 October-November (Box 3)
  Clippings on politics, especially Frook's attempt to debate Eleanor Roosevelt during Frook's bid to be elected representative-at-large on the Law Preservation Party ticket, speaking engagements, legal matters.
- Scrapbook [#11], 1932-1935 (Box 3)
  The bulk of the clippings are from October-December 1934 and concern the attempt of Frooks to engage Eleanor Roosevelt in a political debate. At the back of the scrapbooks are a few clipping from 1932-1933 and 1935.
- Scrapbook [#12], 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  The bulk of the clippings are from November-December 1934, but at the back of the scrapbook are a few from earlier in 1934 and from 1933. The attempt to debate Eleanor Roosevelt continues as a subject, along with the election results (lost by Frooks with only 28 votes).
- Scrapbook [#13], 1917-1937. (Folder 1 of 7), 1917-1920s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  The core content of scrapbook [#13] appears to have been clippings and other documents from 1935-1937. However, a great deal of earlier documents were stuffed inside the book's covers. The scrapbook was unbound during processing and the loose documents were foldered chronologically, with clippings separate from other documents. Among the documents in this first folder are order forms for the book "The American Heart"; publicity flyers and order form for "Love's Law"; poster for Liberty Loan appearance in Beloit, Kansas; a form with original signatures nominating Frooks as a Progressive Independent Party candidate for Congress (1922); and acknowledgement of Frooks's resignation as teacher of continuation school subjects in Vega Baja, Puerto Rico (1923).
- Scrapbook [#13]. 1917-1937. (Folder 2 of 7), 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Among the documents in this folder are a photograph of Frooks with Senator Edward Burke of Nebraska in connection with testimony against President Roosevelt's plan to enlarge the Supreme Court; transparencies for a campaign slide; printed poem "Scars" autographed by author Rella Ritchell (1931); program for testimonial dinner to Edward G. Halsey (1932); program from the laying of the cornerstone of the Supreme Court building, autographed by U.S. President Herbert Hoover; two acknowledgments of nominating petitions and a notice of the drawing for ballot placement, in connection with Frooks's 1934 primary campaign; luncheon program for the Women World War Veterans at the 16th annual convention of the American Legion (1934); platform of the Farmer-Labor-Veteran Party and the list of candidates endorsed by veterans (1934).
- Scrapbook [#13]. 1917-1937. (Folder 3 of 7), 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  This folder holds four brief personal letters (with envelopes) from A.W.W. Woodcock to Frooks.
- Scrapbook [#13]. 1917-1937. (Folder 4 of 7), 1935-1937 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Among the documents in this folder are three messages from Lady Astor(?) in London (1935-36); four silhouette drawings of people, identified by first name (1936); invitation to Independence Day event at the U.S. Ambassador to England's home (1936); admission ticket to the House of Lords (1936); programs at the Hotel Statler in Boston at which Frooks spoke (1936); admission ticket to the White House (1937); ticket and seating list for the 15th annual dinner of the American Law Institute (1937); invitation to Women World War Veterans luncheon, with note from Frooks to Lt. Holden (1937); silhouette of Frooks by Van Court (1937); newsletter "The Sandpiper" from the Hotel Traymore in Atlantic City, with image of Frooks in bathing suit (1937); and a Transradio News Feature with "news for women only" including an article on Frooks (1937).
- Scrapbook [#13]. 1917-1937. (Folder 5 of 7), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Among other documents this folder holds a business card for Counsellor-at-Law Frooks, two announcements of Frooks moving her law office to the Longacre Building, business card for Frooks as editor of the Oyster Bay News, card with Frooks's poem "Our Creed," publicity for book "Civilization Exists?," a pencil drawing of Frooks as a young woman, and certificate of membership in the National Association of Women Lawyers.
- Scrapbook [#13]. 1917-1937. (Folders 6 and 7, of 7). Clippings, 1931-1937 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
- Scrapbook [#14]. (2 folders), 1934-1950 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  The bulk of the scrapbook includes newspaper clippings from 1937-1940, but there are a few from the earlier and later years in the 1934-50 date range. The scrapbook is unbound but remains in the order it was found during processing. The bulk of the content are clippings related to Frooks's activities and opinions in connection with her role as National Commander of the Women World War Veterans (WWWV). These included programs at the 1939 World's Fair, raising funds for a convalescent home, and attempting to de-glamorize war (though insisting that Hitler needed to be dealt with forcefully). There is a program and other ephemera for the American Legion Conventions of 1934, 1937 and 1939, and WWWV stationery.
- Scrapbook [#15], 1918-1953. (Folder 1 of 7), 1918-1939 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  The core content of scrapbook [#15] appears to have been clippings and other documents from about 1934-1941. However, a great deal of earlier and later documents were stuffed inside the book's covers. The scrapbook was unbound during processing and the loose documents were foldered chronologically, with clippings separate from other documents. Among the documents in this first folder are programs for two meetings of the Women of the United States Naval Reserve Force, chaired by Frooks (1918); program booklet for the Dance and Frolic at Midnight event given by the U.S. World War Amputations Association at the Plaza (1929); September 1932 edition of the American Legion Monthly; programs for luncheons of the Women World War Veterans at the American Legion Conventions (1934, 1937, 1939); a Navy recruiting poster for nurses (1936); notice of an election of honorary member Anna Neagle (with four original signatures of officers, all appearing to be in Frooks's handwriting); stationery of Women World War Veterans, Temple of Peace Committee, New York World's Fair Division (1939).
- Scrapbook [#15], 1918-1953. (Folder 2 of 7), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Among the documents in this folder are a program for the Women World War Veterans' (WWWV) Americanisation Day; reunions information and program for WWWV luncheon at the American Legion Convention; program for Daughters of the American Revolution of Florida conference; September 1940 edition of American Legion Magazine; invitation from WWWV to exhibition of the Andrew Carnegie Peace Flags.
- Scrapbook [#15], 1918-1953. (Folder 3 of 7), 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Among other documents, this folder holds a letter from A.G. Spalding & Brothers regarding Frooks's request for information on a "push ball"; note to Commander Tunney wishing to discuss a "physical culturalist" for the Navy; reunions information for the American Legion convention; a circular to the property owners of oil and gas rights in various leases (in Kansas?) from W.H. Rowlands; 6 postcards with personal messages to Frooks; WWWV meeting announcement card; Namm Brooklyn Day Luncheon program; two clippings forwarded to Frooks with note from sender.
- Scrapbook [#15], 1918-1953. (Folder 4 of 7), 1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Among other documents this folder holds a first day cover for the American Bar Association stamp, still sealed, and the program for the ABA's Diamond Jubilee Dinner (both 1953). Among the undated items are three photographs (Frooks in a Red Cross uniform, formal pose; Frooks and four other women at Arlington Cemetery; and the American Andrew Carnegie Peace Flag (others on table in photo); publicity/fundraising pamphlet for the Women World War Veterans (WWWV); WWWV stationery; and WWWV membership application (circa 1937?).
- Scrapbook [#15], 1918-1953. (Folder 5 of 7), 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Holds loose newspaper clippings, primarily from 1940-1941.
- Scrapbook [#15], 1918-1953. (Folders 6 and 7, of 7), 1934-1942 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  Includes primarily newspaper clippings from the core scrapbook pages; most are from 1940, but range randomly from 1934 to 1942. There are some documents other than clippings; among these are: letter from Helene Donley commenting on the effect of the war (WWII) on her, and her hopes for a home for women veterans; photoreproductions of architectural drawings for a proposed Women World War Veterans (WWWV) Memorial Home in Saugerties, architect Carl E. Arenander (1940); four photographs of a large house, possibly the proposed veterans convalescence home?; a publicity mailing for the memorial home in Peekskill (1941); publicity pamphlet for the Women's Service Committee for National Preparedness and Home Defense (1941); Volume 1, Number 1 of the "Woman's Voice Newsletter, edited by Frooks (1938); tearsheet of Frook's article "Women in the World War" in the magazine Fog Horn (1938); Frooks's telegraph to Adolph Hitler asking him to resolve the "Czechoslovakian controversy" amicably (1938); photograph of Florence Caldwell, Florence V. Delaney, Frooks, and Katherine Slowey in Washington DC to lobby for a bonus bill (1935); and the program for the WWWV luncheon in its original coconut tree bark enclosure (1934).
- Scrapbook [#16], 1940, 1950 (Box 2)
  Includes 1940 clippings on Frooks's travels to Miami to speak, including on "Americanism" and "Women Behind the Guns." Many of the scrapbook pages are empty, with glue stains indicating that the contents are likely elsewhere, loose in the collection. 1950 documents includes those related to her campaign for municipal court judge (posters, photograph, blank Democratic Party designating petition for Frook, and official New York County ballots for the primary elections of the Liberal Party, American Labor Party, Democratic Party, and Republican Party).
- Scrapbook [#17], 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  Includes Frooks's articles written for the monthly Murray Hills (N.Y.) News about her overseas travels.
- Scrapbook [#18], 1909, 1917-1920, 1926 (Box 2)
  This scrapbook holds mostly letters, ephemera, programs, certificates, as well as some clippings, related to various aspects of Frooks's early career. Among these are a pencil drawing of Frooks by Hugh Mackay; copyright registration certificate and publicity for "The American Heart"; invitation to a suffrage rally at which Frooks was to speak; 1920 primary election ballot; a thank you note to Frooks from U.S. President Taft (1909); two letters from Woodrow Wilson (1912-13); various documents, especially letters, concerning the Liberty Loan campaigns and recruitment drives of the World War I years; two photographs of a rally, presumably WWI era; a few 1926 clippings related to her legal career; and other documents.
- Scrapbook [#19] (2 folders), 1934-1942 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  This scrapbook (removed from original binder) holds applications to the Women World War Veterans (WWWV) organization as either a "war service member" or as an "associate member." Some associate member forms indicate that the subscription fee can be applied toward the WWWV Convalescent and Recreation Home at Saugerties.
- "Lady Lawyer" Documents (4 folders), 1926-1960s? (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
  These four folders pull together documents found in the collection that clearly relate to Frooks's autobiography, published in the 1970s but in the works long before then. These documents include some typescript drafts, correspondence with co-writers (1950s), outlines, notes, and reference material. Notable documents include the seating list for the dinner given by the Japan Society in honor of Japan Ambassador to the U.S. Katsuji Debuchi and Madame Debuchi (1928); the seating list and program for the dinner given by the George Washington-Sulgrave Institution at the Biltmore in honor of Queen Marie of Roumania (1926); and Frooks's comments before the Senate Judiciary Committee opposing President Roosevelt's "court-packing" proposal. The Deninno murder case is well-represented here with a draft chapter, photograph of Frooks, the defendant and others at the trial, two letters from Catherine Denninno (1927) and a copy of one to her from Frooks, and the men's magazine "True" of March 1938 with an article about the case.
- "My 'World' Series", 1923-1929, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Folder primarily holds clippings of Frooks's column in the New York City Evening World for 1928-29, but also has earlier clips from the Oyster Bay News and a 1934 clipping from the Westchester County Times.
- "Gloria Rouzer / Ione Orde Murder Case, New Orleans, La.", 1929 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Holds four photographs, correspondence, telegrams, clippings, and notes about the case and Frooks's involvement in it.
- "Women Lawyers / Law / Resolutions / Election / Labor Courts", 1957-1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Holds correspondence and other documents related to a variety of legislative proposals and other legal matters connected at least in part to Frooks's involvement with the American Bar Association. Among other documents, includes a proposed resolution for United Nations subsidiary bodies ("Little Assembly") be established in each member nation; suggestions for state legislation sent to Michael H. Prendergast, Chair of the New York Democratic Party; proposed election law reforms; proposed resolution to appoint special masters to help clear the backlog of pending trials; and many notes and proposals on divorce law.
- "Frook Case vs. Applegate / Oldsters", 1937, 1951, 1958-1960, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Folder holds documents on various matters including a case against someone named Applegate for removing trees from Richard Frooks's property in Asbury, Saugerties. This may be the same property that has documents in the file concerning development of a veterans ("oldsters") home (1958-1960). Two apparently unrelated documents are in the file: Frooks's statement to the Senate Judiciary Committee opposing President Franklin D. Roosevelt's proposal to expand the number of seats on the Supreme Court (1937) and a copy of her letter to the editor of the Journal-American concerning "narcotics sold to youth destroying our citizenry." A note transmitting the file to "Laddie" is dated 1984.
- Various Documents, 1897-1901, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Holds various business documents (invoices, insurance policy and receipts, stock certificate) some explicitly related to Frooks's father, others unclear.
- Various Documents, 1900s-1910s, 1908-1919, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 12)